Um
okay. Yeah. So um today's suta
is
Majimanika 62
which is the uh the longer advice to
venerable Raula.
Um at one time the Buddha was staying
near Savati in Jetta's Grove Anaticus
Monastery. Uh when the Buddha roped up
in the morning taking his ball and robe
he enter Savati for arms. There he met
venerable um Rahula who also robbed up
and followed behind him. The Buddha
looked back and said, "Raulah, you
should you should see any kind of form
at all, past, future or present,
internal, external, coarse or fine,
inferior or superior, far or near. All
form as it actually is with right
understanding. This is not mine. I am
not this. This is not myself."
Rahul asked in return only form
auspicious one only form
uh form as well as feeling as perception
activities and consciousness. In other
words the five aggregates. So the five
aggregates should be seen as this is not
mine. I am not this and um this is not
myself. So then the venerable Rahula
thought well who would go to the village
for arms today after being advised
directly by the Buddha. Turning back, he
sat down cross-legged at the root of a
certain tree, set his body straight,
establishing recollection at the four.
Um, venerable Sariputa saw him there and
addressed him. Rahula developed the
recollection of breathing. When
recollection of breathing is developed
and cultivated is very fruitful and very
beneficial. Uh then later in the afternoon, Rahula
Uh then later in the afternoon, Rahula
went out for retreat went to the Buddha
and asked him, "Verable sir, how is the
recollection of the breeding developed
and cultivated so that it's fruitful and
beneficial? So then the Buddha begins the uh longer
So then the Buddha begins the uh longer
instruction saying anything internal
pertaining to oneself that is hard solid
appropriated this includes head of the hair body hair
this includes head of the hair body hair
nails teeth skin flesh senus bones bone
marrow kidneys heart liver diaphragm
spleen lungs intestines
meantry and undigested food feces or
anything else internal pertaining to
oneself that's hard solid and
appropriated This is called the internal
earth element. Both the internal earth
element and the external earth element
are just the earth element. This should
be seen as it is with right
understanding. This is not mine. I'm not
this. This is not myself.
Having seen it with right understanding,
one grows disenchanted with the earth
element. One reads the mind of the
passion for the earth element. Then goes
to describe the water element. So uh
water element may be internal or
external. What is internal water
element? Anything internal pertaining to
oneself that's watery and appropriated.
This includes bile, flame, pus, blood,
sweat, fat, tears, grease, saliva, snot,
synovial, fluid, urine, anything else
internal pertaining to oneself that's
watery or appropriated. This is called
the eternal internal water element. Both
internal and external water element are
the water just the water element. So
this should be seen with right
understanding like this is not mine. I'm
not this, this is not myself and so on.
So the fire element, the fire element
internally, it's anything that's fire,
fiery, warm, hot, appropriated.
Obviously, this includes uh the warmth,
that which warms, that which ages, that
which heats you up when feverish, that
which properly digests food and drink,
anything else internal pertaining to
oneself that's fire, fire fiery or
appropriated, and appropriated. This is
called the internal fire element. both
internal and external fire elements
there same needs to be seen as this is
not mine that's not myself I'm not this
and that's not myself in order for mine
to be rid of the passion for the fire
element and then the um air element goes
that anything airy pertaining to oneself
so winds that go up and down winds in
the belly of the bowels winds that flow
through the limbs in breath out breath
anything else internal pertaining to
oneself that's airy or and appropriated
This is called the internal air element.
Both internal and external means the air
element is there.
So this also needs to be seen as this is
not mine. I'm not this this is not
myself. So the space element is added here for
So the space element is added here for
practical reasons. Well, I'll explain
that later. So any space element that
may be internal or external. What is
internal space element? Anything
internal and pertaining to oneself that
is space spacious and appropriated
includes ear canals, nostrils, mouth,
space for swallowing what is eaten and
drunk, space where it stays, space for
excreting it from the nether regions or
anything else internal pertaining to
oneself that space spacious and
appropriated. This is called the
internal space element and both internal
space element and the external space
element means the space element is just
there. This should be seen with right
understanding. This is not mine. I'm not
this. This is not myself. Having seen it
with right understanding, he grows
disenchanted with the space element. He
reads the mind of passion for the space
element. So then the Buddha gives him a bit of a
So then the Buddha gives him a bit of a
more kind of even more practical um
context to develop. Says develop your
mind like earth or your mind is added
here obviously for the sake of clarity
but just says develop yourself like
earth. Just develop like earth. When you
develop like earth, a reason agreeable
and disagreeable pressures will not
occupy your mind. Suppose they were to
toss both clean and unclean things on
the earth like feces, urine, spit, pass,
and blood. The earth isn't horrified,
repelled or disgusted because of this.
In the same way, developed develop like
earth. For when you develop like earth,
a reason agreeable and disagreeable
pressures will not endure with a grip on
your mind.
Develop like water. For when you develop
like water, a reason agreeable and
disagreeable pressure will not occupy
your mind. Suppose there's there were to
wash both clean and unclean things in
the water like feces, urine, spit,
passing blood, the water isn't
horrified, repelled, disgusted because
of this. So in the same way develop like
water when you develop like water a
reason agreeable and disagreeable
pressures will not um will not endure
with a grip on your mind. then develop
like fire kind of in the same way so
that there isn't an agreeable
disagreeable pressures do not occupy
your mind because the fire burns both
clean and unclean things and the fire
isn't horrified repelled and disgusted
because of any of that. Uh develop your
mind like air because the wind blows on
both clean and unclean things like feces
urine spirit pass and blood and the wind
isn't horrified repelled basically it's
indifferent. So in the same way you
should develop um like earth, water,
fire, air so that arisen agreeable and
disagreeable pressures passer common
translations contact will not endure
with a grip on your mind. So basically
your mind will be above above that which
is pressuring it.
And the last it's develop like space for
when develop like space a reason
agreeable disagreeable pressures won't
occupy your mind just as a space is not
established anywhere in the same way um
develop like space so don't be
established anywhere
u then it goes into develop friendliness
so that any ill will be abandoned
develop compassion so that any annoyance
will be abandoned develop contentment so
that any discontent will be abandoned
develop equinimity
So that any resistance patiga will be
abandoned. Um develop perception of non- beauty,
Um develop perception of non- beauty,
develop the perception of impermanence
and then it goes at the end develop the
recollection of breathing. You know that
the whole question started with
um and um so well before we go to the
recollection of breathing so let's just
quickly address these well maybe not so
quickly. So the whole um element
contemplation like um obviously you know
people can can can you know start
abstractly in a sense of uh thinking
about solid uh hard things that are
earth that are made of stone and so on
just to get the idea.
The point is to discern that internal
earth element.
Um
that which is usually overlooked, that
which is usually um not seen, that which
is usually peripheral, that which is
usually assumed and taken for granted
and appropriated as every passage here
says. So the the point is not to observe
or or or or or monitor or or attend to
with your senses to earth, water, fire,
earth. The point is to include basically
things just broad things in your
experience that you generally overlook
because your attention is too absorbed
with this thing or the other. Uh include
those peripheral things so to see them
as partaking in the same nature as this
obvious earth around you obvious fire uh
water and so on. That's why in other
sutas when the Buddha talked about the
elements, the element contemplation, it
always kind of starts by well look at
these these great mountains and see how
they erode and get destroyed. What is to
be said of this little kind of
insignificant weak soft body.
So the point is um you could try and and
kind of induce these these um feelings
of like ah okay my body will change
because the great earth element changed
because the great water element changed
but um in order for that to not be
abstract. uh there needs to be something in your
uh there needs to be something in your
experience as a whole that you now
recognize that you now see as that
internal earth element that internal
solid that internal aspect of the airy
watery fiery space. So that's what I
mean like it's not about uh discerning
it through your direct attention and
figuring it out. It's about getting used
to that which is already there. So
instead of trying to attend to your body
directly to see hair, nails, teeth, see
it at the back of your mind without
needing to attend to it directly, but
know that there is hair, uh, nails,
teeth, flesh, seniors and bone. They has
to be there. So that peripheral
knowledge that's not directly attended.
So basically you have to refrain from
your tendency from the from the desire
to directly attend it and dissect it
because it will be object of your
senses. You don't want to see the body on the
You don't want to see the body on the
level of the object of your senses,
which is sight, sound, smell, taste,
sensations. You want to see the body on
the level of the sense basis. You want
to see the internal
body, the one that's appropriated, the
one that doesn't directly appear, the
one that's always overlooked because
that's where the problem is.
So the whole practice of the four
elements, it's not about
memorizing all these things that the
Buddha listed are uh solid and and
earthy and watery and fiery. It's more
like discerning any of those aspects.
And sure, even if you think in those
specific terms, that's fine obviously,
but you need to think of them uh
peripherally. You need to be seeing them
peripherally. It needs to start to um pertain to the
It needs to start to um pertain to the
knowledge of what's already there as
opposed to oh things are only there when
I look at them directly. The moment my
attention lapses I forget about him and
that's that's not well pretty much that
no contemplation works like that. So, so
the point of the four great element
contemplation is to always have a
reference point of your background of
that peripheral thing that endures that
shares the same nature like things that
you do access with your senses directly.
Sight, sounds, smell, taste, sensations.
And when you look at those things that
are obviously changing, you don't need
to convince yourself that okay, so now
because of that, my internal body will
also change. No, by seeing it
sufficiently enough that it's the same
thing as in shares the same nature as it
says both internal or external doesn't
matter what kind of um specific
differences would have been perceived
and evolved fundamentally anything
pertaining to internal anything
pertaining to external that you can
observe means the earth element is just
there and that's what you want to um
teach your mind that's what you want to
sink In you want to know that anything
internal as I said doesn't matter like
vague clear big or small past future
anything internal anything external
shares the same nature so then when the
obvious nature of external things you
seen or you get reminded of the internal
counterpart cannot not be affected by it
that's what I mean like that's why I
said like you won't have to convince
yourself then that this internal is also
So like that external because it is
because you've seen it enough that it
pertain that it pertains to ex that
shares exactly the same nature. So if
all these things of that nature are
obvious subject to change
nothing else then that shares that
nature cannot escape it. So that's how
you include that's how you contemplate
this um the four elements in that sense
that would result in this passion
because the entire world of passion
exists and you ignoring the peripheral
and being absorbed in the object of your
senses obviously being mesmerized and
trapped through the through the pleasure
that you get uh through avoidance of an
aversion towards pain uh offers of
management offers of escape and so on.
You keep overlooking the bigger picture
the experience as a whole. how we say it
and that's why even if you tell yourself
oh yes I know this body is like these
great elements you're not really feeling
it on that level
so the the the real contemplation is yes
contemplate how these great elements
change how you cannot be exempt from
that and then feel it feel how you
cannot be exempt from that and don't try
to then psychologize and get rid of that
uncomfortable feeling that might come up
no just leave it there because that's
how it feels
to take something that's not yours as
yours to appropriate it feels dangerous.
Don't try to I must get get rid of this
danger because it's unpleasant. I must I
must concentrate. I must meditate. I
must calm down or something. No, don't
make it worse, but at the same time
recognize, no, no, no, this danger is
there affecting me only because I'm
taking what I shouldn't be taking up.
So, if you leave it there long enough,
don't try to get rid of it. Don't act
out of it for sure. You'll stop taking
it
when the danger doesn't touch touch you
anymore. You know, you would have let go
of the bait.
So that's the earth, water, fire, same
whichever. You don't even have to go out
earth and then water. Just take any on a
different day. Doesn't matter. You all
they all stand for the same principle.
They all stand for that same peripheral
that's usually being overlooked. They
all stand for that lack of or
insufficient yon to say to put it that
way. And the space element is included
And the space element is included
because yes, it's not primary on the
level of the four elements, but it's
it's practical like you could see
everything else and you could kind of
see or even think space in between. So
now you include the space in between as
the element as the thing that changed
that's defined by things that's in space
and so on. Either way, the point is you
can't appropriate it even if you want
to. So you want to then recognize that
that which you do appropriate your
internal sense bases, eyes, ears, nose,
body and so on that that too cannot be
appropriated even if you want to. But it
it will take a while for that to sink in
and for the duration of that whole
practice you need to have been and and
and sustain your withdrawal from unh
wholesome states um uh virtue restraint
and everything else. just without it
it's like well you're not going to get
anywhere. Um so then these kind of more um poetic
Um so then these kind of more um poetic
uh simile is develop your mind like
earth develop yourself like water like
fire in the same basically the context you
in the same basically the context you
strive for. If the whole thing is
unownable means the whole thing is not
yours means the whole thing is not your
problem. So whatever your eyes see here
smell taste touch you won't be desiring
it and you certainly won't be repelled
by it because it's not your problem.
Um so then he goes on to develop
friendliness for develop friendliness
and he will ill will be abandoned. Um
maybe we can address that later these
four brahma viharas. Um so let's go back
to the uh recollection of the breathing
then it says uh so it will be obviously
very fruitful and beneficial and then it
goes to the standard description at the
end of it saying uh when a big gone to
wilderness the roof of a tree the roof
of a tree the root of a tree or to an
empty hut. Um
where was I?
Oh yeah, the screen changed.
So, uh, gone to wilderness or to root of
a tree or an empty hut. Sits down
cross-legged. Um, sets the body straight
and establishes a recollection at a
four. Recollected, he breathes in,
recollected, he breathes out. Breathing
in long, he understands, I'm breathing
in long. Breathing out long, he
understands. I'm breathing out long.
Breathing in short, he understands. I'm
breathing in short. Breathing out short,
he understands I'm breathing out short.
He trains like this, experiencing the
whole body. I'll breathe in. He trains
on this experiencing the whole body.
I'll breathe out. Calming the body
activity. I'll breathe in. He trains
calming the body activity. I'll breathe
out. So, you can already see
how it starts. Recollected. So,
nonforfully he breathes in.
Nonforgetfully he breathes out. That's
the practice in and of itself.
There's no um new steps that you add to
this. Everything else that follows is
within this this thing.
Recollected, he breathes in.
Recollected, he breathes out. That
doesn't change. So if you think uh if
you go to the next step, quote unquote,
I'll breathe in long and you already
lost your recollection, you are not
breathing in long with understanding.
So in other words, practice
recollectively breathing in,
recollectively breathing out at the
peripheral. That's kind of the whole point. Um, in
That's kind of the whole point. Um, in
order to know that you're already
breathing, you don't need to concentrate
on the parts of your body to reveal to
you that you're already breathing. The
knowledge that you're breathing is
already there. So, don't forget it.
Don't forget that the body is already
breathing. See it at the back of your
mind. Don't stop doing things in the
sense of like um I don't know if you're
walking or sitting or something.
Obviously, you can't be too occupied
with your attention like reading and and
and and doing stuff that would take too
much of your attention. But you don't
have to concentrate on top of
withdrawing from activities in order to
see what's already there. You don't need
to concentrate on your breath to know
that it's there. So just go to a
non-disturbed like quiet place. Um bring
your mindfulness to the four as they
said param.
Um, the point is just okay, stop being
distracted and sit down and recognize
what's already there. So, let that
memory of your breath that's happening
right there while you're remembering it.
Let it let it be there in the
peripheral. Let it endure. You don't
have to, okay, now I do this and now I
do that and where does that lead? No,
no, no. It leads nowhere. Leads there.
Where it begins, that's where it ends.
It begins with recollect. He breathes
in. Recollect. he breathes out. That's
the beginning and the end.
So I know that there's a tendency to
overthink it because obviously
all the contemporary um meditations and
not just even Buddhists have mystified
the breath long enough and now there is
all these implicit assumptions and hopes
and and and tendencies associated with
this practice. But really mindfully he
breathes in, mindfully he breathes out,
nonforfully he breathes in, nonforfully
he breathes out. See how that feels.
Just sit down and let the body breathe
and try to not completely forget about
it. The mind will come up with stuff but
don't completely
drift away. That's the point
as the other sutras do say that I think
it was that um Arita suta in Majimo I
don't remember who said basically this
is how he practices the breeding
recollector he breathes in recollected
he breathes out he abandons all the pata
he abandons sensuality of the past and
the future and present and all the
patiga in regard to the body is also
been abandoned that's how he fulfills it
and the Buddha says yeah sure that is
obviously the way however it's not
complete and then he goes to uh uh
expound on these other additional steps
which are not steps. It's just
refinements of the refinement aspects of
the same principle which is recollected
breathe in recollected breathe out. So
if that becomes established like in
other words when doesn't matter how much
your attention shifts and goes from here
to there at the back of your mind if
it's been broadened enough there's
always going to be uh at least a grain
of recognition that there is breathing
in and breathing out that's it.
So that's how you would then you could
refine that. So now within that
peripheral recognition of breathing in
breathing out you would recognize that
you're breathing in long that you're
breathing out long. Before it was just
breathing in and out. Doesn't matter how
it was too much basically to to discern
that. But now you can discern. You can
discern that it's long. You can discern
that it's short.
And u and you understand that you see
it. You don't need to you don't need to
attend to it. You don't need to monitor
every second of it. Quite the opposite.
If you do, you will lose the sight of
it. That's kind of the point of the
entire any practice of sati is to
unabsorb you from from from your senses
from your observations from your overly
concentrated attitude. That's why I keep
saying modern meditations and and
practices are taking you in the
completely opposite direction where the
dharma is.
So once you define even that like now
peripherally not just that you know
you're breathing in not just that you're
not forgetting that you're breathing out
you are also knowing and understanding
that you're breathing in long and that
you're breathing out long that you're
breathing in short that you're breathing
out short. So the knowledge of that has
been even modified. In other words the
sight the range of your peripheral
without needing to attend to it directly
has been expanded.
So then you can train further. He trains
like this. Experiencing the whole body
I'll breathe in. So what does that mean?
Well that means that within the memory
of the inb breath that is happening
right now I shall outline this ex
internal body. This body that is
previous paragraph would have been
talking about.
So as I said the internal body is always
overlooked. That's why through
developing anapanosati correctly in this
indirect method you are developing the
peripheral which means whether you want
it or not you are developing the
internal recognition of the internal
body. So you could now make make the
actual like a more active effort that
within that peripheral you discern the
extent of your physicality without
needing to directly attend to it because
if you do it's not the body you're
seeing it's the objects of your senses
of your body. So that's why it's like he
trains like this. In other words, make
the effort to peripherally once you
become familiar with it outline that
which body is that full sphere of
internal that which shares that nature
of these four great elements externally
that are obviously changing and so on.
So experiencing the whole body I'll
breathe in experiencing the whole body
I'll breathe out he trains further
calming the bodily activity I'll breathe
in. So see you don't calm the bodily
activity without even recognizing the
extent of that body. You can't calm your
physicality if you don't even see the
phenomenon of physicality there
peripherally. So that's why once you see it now you
So that's why once you see it now you
could actually calm it.
So calming the body activity I'll
breathe in. Calming the body activity
I'll breathe out. Those are by the way
still all refinements of this very
thing. Recollect he breathes in.
Recollect he breathes out. They're not
extra steps. Then he trains like this.
Experiencing joy, I'll breathe in.
Experiencing joy, I'll breathe out. See,
now you're getting even on a on a on a
subtler level, which is not even
so concerned with physicality anymore.
Now you should just train. See, if you
would have refined your indirect
attention on that peripheral level to
the point of calming the physicality
without direct falling into trap of
directly attending to it, you could now
just experience joy
like generate joy on the level of those
feelings there peripherally.
So, experiencing joy, I'll breathe in,
experiencing joy, I'll breathe out.
Experiencing ease, I'll breathe in.
Experiencing ease, I'll breathe out.
So these are kind of precursors.
Basically, it's about the feelings that
are obviously, as I said before, they're
kind of neither in your physicality nor
on the level where your mind is, but
they're factually there. So when the
physicality is tamed enough,
sufficiently um discerned on that peripheral level,
um discerned on that peripheral level,
what's left there, what whatever's felt
there, you could then actually calm it.
You could ease it.
You could be joyful in it so to speak.
You could experience happiness on
account of it because it's already quite
purified obviously. So then the next
step is experiencing the mind activity.
In other words, you're going to find
your mind active. That chitta that
animal will have some activity to some
extent. And you want to outline that just as as
And you want to outline that just as as
you were outlining the the whole body,
just as you were outlining the feelings
through joy um and ease. Now you're
outlining the mind, experiencing the
mind activity.
Why do you need to outline the mind?
Well, outline the mind in a very
accurate sense on that far developed
peripheral level that you're seeing on
that internal in that internal dimension
to put it that way. Uh experiencing,
discerning, outlining the mind is a
precursor to step two. Now you could
calm it. Now you could really just calm
that animal down. Just tell it to okay
sit down while I breathe in I shall be
seating this this mind while I breathe
out I shall be seating it further so
until it just calms down once it's
completely calm seated it is you can
experience it even more as in outline it
clearer in its calm immovable state so
experiencing the mind I'll breathe in
experiencing the mind I'll breathe out
gladdening the mind literally gladdening
the animal like gladen it uplift it
because you are on the level of directly
communicating to it through your
indirect development of not directly
attending to the peripheral level where
you've been discerning these things more
and more and more.
So once you once you calm the mind, once
you outline the mind, once you calm it,
once you gladdened it, you can compose
it, you can liberate it, you could tell it
you can liberate it, you could tell it
basically, turn away, turn away from
everything that you've been going after
because both of us see now that it's not
worth it. And the mind will listen
because you have showed it that it's not
worth it. Um, how you show that it's not
worth it? Well, you showed it through
the perception of impermanence,
perception of non- beauty, uh
development of friendliness, compassion,
contentment, equinimity. But anyway,
we'll deal with it later.
So, he goes here to do the same
actually. So, he trains further. Now
that the mind is being liberated and
it's listening and it's composed, you
then maintain the perspective of
impermanence while you breathe in. So
while breathe in while breathe out just
means basically it's another way of
saying the peripheral uh dimension
discerned through not directly attending
it maintains it's maintained it endures.
So within that you now think of
impermanence. Within that you think of
dispassion. You think of sensation. You
think of relinquishment. These are the
perceptions that now are directly
talking to your mind which is also over
there peripherally where that
physicality is which is why you started
with physicality and feelings and so on
before you were able to outline the mind
fully. Obviously you've got some idea.
So that's why when recollection of
breeding when developed in culture in
this way it's very fruit beneficial. In
other words, there will be nothing that
you haven't addressed.
And when the recollection of breathing
is developed and cultivated this way,
even one's final breath ceases
knowingly, not unknowingly. So if
anaponic is to be understood, how people
think of it today is I must concentrate
on my breath in order to know it. You're
never going to be able to know your
final breath because death always comes
as a surprise. So this is the very exact
point that the Buddha wants to
illustrate here is that
even final breath which is always a
surprise to an untrained mind cannot not
be included in that sufficiently
developed peripheral recognition of
nondirectly attending to your breathing
yet knowing that it's there. So if you
would have developed that thoroughly on
a day-to-day basis, even the utmost
surprise cannot make you not see that that extent
cannot make you not see that that extent
cannot make you not can make you lose
perspective and ignore it. So even the
last breath will be known not because
you'll be waiting hunting for it there
to not miss it like a like a bullet
train or something. No, it will be known
because it will be included. it will be
included because your mind has already
surmounted the whole thing. It's in
front of it how you pretty much started
the practice.
So that's what the Buddha said was
obviously very pleased.
Um
so let me just um
and a few more things. Yeah. So they
were back onto the the friendliness and
like um it kind of like oh develop
friendliness to to abandon the um
ill will. So people think aha see so I
do meta. Well develop friendliness
nobody says you shouldn't develop it.
It's it's how you develop it. What do
you do about it? Does does develop
friendliness mean go and think positive
thoughts about people that you hate? But
does that mean your hate came from those
people? So, does your real will come
from people that upset you?
If not, then why do you need to think
positive thoughts of those people when
they are not the problem?
Because if your real will does come from
those people, well, good luck overcoming
it because their actions will never be
in your control. And if their actions
are truly the cause, the beginning of
your ill will, you can never uproot it.
You can only put a perfect patch on it
every time it comes up.
So yes, develop friendliness, but that
still doesn't justify the contemporary
ideas of meta which are absolutely
ridiculous. So how do you then develop friendliness?
So how do you then develop friendliness?
Well, by recognizing the roots of your
aversion. And what is the root of your aversion?
And what is the root of your aversion?
Well, it's your own resistance to your
own sense basis.
So first, it's not sense objects,
therefore others or non- others. It's
absolutely irrelevant. Second, if you're
not withdrawn from s sense objects
fully, thoroughly through virtue and
restraint, you're not even going to
outline the the internal dimension as we
just been through as we just discussed.
So there is a reason the Buddha said
these practices after like you would
have been outlining everything through
the peripheral recognition of the nature
of the elements that your own
physicality partakes in.
So then when you are basically say you
would have been practicing those
contemplations regularly
you want to you want to sit down and
meditate contemplate sit down and start
pondering on this nature start
developing the peripheral discernment
including things into it so so that
nothing is left out so that you don't
even have to go around thinking about
those things actively through your
focused attention because they'll be on
the level of the knowledge now they're
known they are understood you can go
about your day knowing doing those
things. So once you were to practice
that then yes you could then also on
that same indirect level practice
friendliness literally develop the
non-ill will towards your own sense
bases. So these the sense bases these these
So these the sense bases these these
sense domains that have their own
feeding grounds as so to say when the
sight sounds smell taste touches slash
sensations land if they're uncomfortable
you twitch the sense bases twitch you're
averse to that
there is resistance there is piga that's
the root of all hate
I mean you wouldn't be able to hate your
neighbor who said something upset ing if
you didn't hear what he said.
But obviously those levels are not seen.
So all you see is the neighbor. All you
see is his intentions. All you see how
he's been doing this all the time. And
you just keep winding yourself up around
your own projected views. But
fundamentally it's really your own ears,
eyes, nose, body that you're resisting.
That is what your the root of your
aversion is. So spread matter to
yourself. Not in a sense love yourself
because that would be equally ignorant.
But recognize that the aversion comes
from you not being trained in regard to
your own internal internal sense basis
these things that that that
sight sounds smell taste touches land on
so to speak. So if you choose to on that
see like if you would have been
developed in regard to physicality
rightly now you could say you could be
recognizing the internal domains you
know where where the pressure comes up
where the aversion manifests and not be
averse towards that. So don't be averse
towards that pang of aversion that
happens internally. But by that point
obviously you would have had to stop
blaming the world, stop blaming others.
Even if it's like you know the most
justifiable thing to do it's because of
you know what he said she did or
something you know no all of that is
second the root of aversion it's always
my own resistance to my own sense bases
sense organs you can say that way. So
that's pretty much what what triggers
everything else that then proliferates
and spreads and gets projected onto the
world and actions that follow. So if you
develop non-resistance, if you develop
friendliness, just be a friend towards
your own internal senses when they are
averse. Just like a friend say, okay,
you know, let's not make this worse.
Let's not act out of it. Calm down. The
mind's going to come up and says, no,
no, but it's it's because of he said if
you don't do anything about it, he'll do
it again and they'll do it again and the
whole thing will go through. It's like
it doesn't matter. All of those are
traps. All of those are to make me act
towards it and overlook where the real
problem is, which is my own aversion
towards this internal thing that I have
not been trained myself in regard to.
But if you do, again, there's absolutely
nothing that can come from the world
that could surprise you or or make you
overlook that. So you would be
abandoning ill will by killing it at its
roots. And then same goes for the um the other
And then same goes for the um the other
four braharas. The point is they're all
developed on that progressively more
refined state of the peripheral of the
discernment what's internal and further
and further and further. But yeah, just
stick with meta if you want on that
level and you will be unable to hate
because the framework of non-hate
towards the root towards the trigger of
aversion which is your sense basis when
they encounter things that are
disagreeable that framework doesn't
change. That framework is now
unfaltering. That framework cannot be
lost because again you have a direct
verification that
no amount of pressure can touch you. No
amount of pressure can cause that
aversion and and and snowball into
actions and so on. But again as the
other sutras also say in order to
develop Brahma viharas you need to dwell
like a Brahma. You need to be thoroughly
withdrawn from all the unh wholesome. So
that is this internal physicality and
aspect and the sense basis because the
Buddha compared the sense basis is
they're negative. They're like empty
empty village and so on that that you
cannot possibly uh just put in front of
you and see it like you would see sight,
sounds, smell, taste, touches. So they
are the utmost fundamental negative.
Um so and then goes yeah those
perceptions of impermanence and I
address that. So the the point so as I
maybe it was clear but maybe I can just
repeat um like if if you just if you
just read this suta the um
just the part about anapanosati
and uh if if you're able to just put
everything else you heard about
anapanosati aside all the Burmese
methods all the energy manipulations all
the nostril watching just just forget
about all of it just read it on its own
terms see what honestly would come up to your
see what honestly would come up to your
mind as as what would I do how would I
go about doing this
and really try to understand it on that
level because that's the point as I said
people fall into these expectations
because they learned it they learned
about it through these techniques and
methods and so on but just don't try and
do anapanasi
sit down recognize what's there as we
said recollected breathe in breathe out
and stick with that because that should
be enough, by the way, to outline the
entire domain inter of the internal even
more clearly and certainly should be
enough to um remove all the partig
eventually that that resistance that
aversion that you have towards a version
of your sense uh sense bases that will
also be abandoned. So if you just even
do that that that that that uh basic
general um practice of nonforgetfulness of
um practice of nonforgetfulness of
breathing you you would be free from
sensuality and ill will.
Um
so
if you put everything you learn about it
aside as I said like you know I can give
you oh this is what anaparasati is about
but no really just sit down with it
yourself and just just try and not forget about
and just just try and not forget about
your breathing and see where it takes
you so
it can kind of eventually sort of build
up and paint a different picture of what
anapanas is actually heart. But
obviously, as I said, if you're just
doing it on top of your non-verirtue,
non-restraint, good luck. I mean, technically speaking,
good luck. I mean, technically speaking,
anapana was taught to sautanas as a form
of satipana,
it was a form that was taught to at
least sautanas.
But again, that's not to say you
shouldn't be trying it, but you should
be trying to do it rightly because in
order to practice anapanas, you need to
be seeing your mind. In order to see
your mind, you need to have been
discerning chitan sufficiently. And
that's already a step away from uh
sapati. So you want to practice anaponi do it
So you want to practice anaponi do it
but don't do it at the expense of the
actual training
uh actual training in virtue training in
in in withdrawal training in enduring
things on the right level and everything
else we talk about it on and on and on.
So
um
in the same sense like if we are
withdrawn from as I said falling into
the common expectations of what anapanas
is all about and just read the suta
what is the purpose of it so you could
already see it's not a beginner's
practice obviously you know the Buddha
went through all these other stuff and
the elements and and and maintaining
these contexts before say you know you
are equipped to practice anapanasati but
anyway That doesn't mean you can't get
the right idea of what it's about. And u
you realize that since the whole point
is to be developing that u peripheral
the recognition of peripheral the
non-forgetfulness means it's exactly as
I said it's exactly the opposite of the
common idea of concentration and
absorption practices. So the the main
purpose of anapanosati is to unabsorb
you from your senses.
By being unabsorbed you get a full
picture. You get that negative of what
those senses refer to, what the sense
objects refer to, what the senses, sense
object point to and that's how you start
to outline the physicality, outline the
feelings, outline the moods.
So, so yeah, you know, you won't be able
to just start practicing anapanasi
rightly because it's really a training
because it's really a training
um of that as we said mindfulness of
that recollectedness that that broadens
the peripheral recognition without
needing to directly attend to you attend
to it. But it doesn't mean you shouldn't
you shouldn't be thinking about it or
trying to do it especially if it's
paired with your virtue with your sense
restraint with training in virtue. I
don't want to just I keep saying with
virtue, but that implies we're training
in virtue. Not just blindly keeping the
virtue, but actually training in the
principles by bod speech and mind.